Travis A. Martin

(1-206) 659-6147 • tamartin@gmail.com • View my portfolio at: travisamartin.com

Profile

I wear multiple hats: I am a senior technical writer, content strategist, and UX researcher. I enjoy wrangling complex problems and answering the question "Why?" with qualitative and quantitative data.

Specialties: content development, content strategy, information design, user research, user-centered design

Skills: DITA; XMetaL; quantitative and qualitative research: field study, focus group, cognitive walkthrough, interview, survey, content audit, heuristic evaluation, card sort, A/B test, wireframes, prototypes

Experience

Dell EMC Isilon

Senior Technical Content Developer & Content Strategist, May 2012–Present

- Above all, I help customers build knowledge by creating clear, concise, visually appealing, user-centered
 technical content. This includes, but isn't limited to: UI text, online help, knowledge base articles, blog
 posts, videos, upgrade guides, administration guides, compatibility guides, and white papers.
- Use a combination of content audits, data analysis, benchmarking, and user research to produce content that meets business objectives and customers' goals.
- Co-founded the Information Development Strategy team. We are a team of content and user experience professionals who conduct user research with customers and provide guidance to developers and writers on matters of user experience and content strategy.
- Created Isilon's first user personas using ethnographic research methods: interviews, surveys, and site visits. Trained other teams on how to create and use personas.
- Collaborated with UX and engineering teams to create style guidelines for the OneFS operating system and its companion product, InsightIQ.
- Write customer-facing UI text for the OneFS and InsightIQ user interfaces, including text for field labels, button names, tooltips, in-app help, and error messages.
- Led a successful company-wide campaign to redesign and standardize the release notes for Dell EMC products, so that when customers purchase and combine different Dell EMC products, the information experience is the same.
- Developed and advanced the idea of Information Hubs—curated lists of related information based on the hub-and-spoke model—across the company to improve the findability of information for customers. Example: https://community.emc.com/docs/DOC-44304
- Mentor team members on authoring tools, team processes, global writing standards, content reuse, and DITA best practices.

Tyler Technologies (in partnership with Microsoft)

User Assistance Lead, 2008-2012

- Lead technical writer. Mentored team members on authoring tools, team processes, global writing standards, content reuse.
- Planned, researched, wrote, published, and updated documentation for Microsoft Dynamics AX. Deliverables included online help, release notes, and tech notes.
- Wrote customer-facing UI text for field labels, button names, tooltips, in-app help, and error messages.

Contract positions at Microsoft, Real Networks, AT&T Wireless Quality Assurance Engineer, 1996–2008

- Lead QA Engineer with planning and project management responsibilities. Developed project plans, managed team schedule, and tracked project delivery.
- Tested the design and functionality of new software applications and websites. Tests included functional tests, regression tests, stress tests, and build verification tests.
- Wrote training guides, test plans, test cases, and test reports.
- Wrote user stories and use case scenarios for software projects based on customer interviews, surveys, and competitive benchmarking.

Education

University of Washington

- MS, Technical Communication
- BA, Linguistics

Honors and Awards

Dell EMC

- Dell EMC Gold Excellence Award
 For improving the findability of product documentation through Information Hubs
- Dell EMC Silver Excellence Award
 For creating high-value troubleshooting guides based on content audits and user research
- Dell EMC Bronze Excellence Award
 For training teams on how to use web analytics for content planning

Publications

Rose, E., Racadio, R., Martin, T., Girard, D., & Kolko, B. (2017). Expert yet vulnerable: Understanding the needs of transit dependent riders to inform policy and design. *The Journal of Community Informatics*, 13(1). Retrieved from http://ci-journal.net/index.php/ciej/article/view/1262/1241